Register to the United States. Subversive Activities Control Board records
Hoover Institution Archives
United States. Subversive Activities Control Board records
1950-1973
71009
United States. Subversive Activities Control Board
90 manuscript boxes (37.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Hearing transcripts, decisions, and reports, relating to determination of communist-action and communist-front organizations in the United States.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1971.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Duplicate set of records in: National Archives and Records Administration.
Historical Note
The United States Subversive Activities Control Board was created in 1950 in conjunction with enactment of the Internal Security Act of 1950. This act, known as the McCarran Act after its author Senator Pat McCarran, did not outlaw the Communist Party but sought to secure its control through regulation (or perhaps more likely, its dissolution rather than submit to such control). It required registration with the United States government of domestic "communist-action organizations" (defined as organizations substantially under the control of "the world-wide communist movement") and of domestic "communist-front organizations" (defined as organizations substantially under the control of "communist-action organizations"). The Attorney General might petition the Subversive Activities Control Board to order the registration of specific organizations under one or the other of these rubrics. The Board, made up of five members appointed by the President and confirmed by the Senate, was in turn empowered to hold hearings to determine whether these were indeed "communist-action" or "communist-front" organizations, and if so, to order them to register as such. Registration entailed annual provision of financial records and membership lists.
The Communist Control Act of 1954 added a third task for the Board: that of determining "communist-infiltrated" organizations, principally labor unions. "Communist-infiltrated" unions were not to be required to register, but were deprived of the collective bargaining rights guaranteed to other unions.
The Board opened hearings on the Communist Party, U.S.A., and, after hearing voluminous testimony, issued a report in 1953 ordering it to register as a "communist-action organization." The Communist Party appealed through the courts, challenging the constitutionality of the McCarran Act and alleging the Board's report to have been based in part on perjured testimony. When the case reached it in 1956, the Supreme Court found sufficient merit in the latter contention to remand the case to the Board for review. A modified Board report reaffirmed its earlier finding and again ordered the Communist Party to register. Another round of legal appeals ensued, with the Supreme Court upholding the Board ruling in a 5-4 decision in 1961. The Communist Party continued to refuse to register, however, maintaining that a party official certifying his party under the stigma of subversion would be placing himself in a position tantamount to self-incrimination.
The Board met this argument head on by invoking a hitherto-unused section of the McCarran Act providing for registration of individual members of "communist-action organizations." Beginning in 1962 it held hearings and issued orders to several individuals, mainly well-known Communist Party leaders, to register. Consequent appeals reached the Supreme Court in 1965, and the Court responded by striking down the individual registration portion of the McCarran Act as being in violation of the Fifth Amendment protection against self-incrimination. Looking one chess move ahead, it was apparent to all that there could be no possibility of forcing any of its officers to register the Communist Party, or any other organization, as subversive.
The Board had meanwhile held hearings regarding, and issued registration orders to, a number of other organizations, all associated with the Communist Party, mainly in the "communist-front organizations" category. These had generated similar rounds of legal appeals. In the post-1965 period the Board initiated hearings on only two more organizations and a very few individuals. Its decisions in these cases stated Board findings of communist affiliation, but did not include any registration orders. Clearly the Board was unable to carry out the function originally envisaged for it. Moreover the national political climate had changed since 1950. President Richard M. Nixon issued an executive order abolishing the Board, and it wound up its affairs in 1973. During its 23 years of existence, it held extensive hearings, took voluminous testimony, and issued a number of decisions and orders, but did not succeed in securing the registration of any "communist-action", "communist-front" or "communist-infiltrated" organizations or of any individuals.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Subversive Activities Control Board records in the Hoover Institution Archives are a substantially complete duplicate set of the Board's official records now in the National Archives and Records Administration. They were acquired from the Board in 1971, with subsequent increments during its winding-up phase.
The great bulk of the collection consists of mimeographed verbatim transcripts of hearing proceedings, most of which had been completed by the end of 1957. Both Department of Justice and organization or individual under investigation were represented by attorneys during hearings and had the right to call witnesses and to cross-examine opposing witnesses. The mass of testimony affords a wealth of information regarding the operations of the Communist Party and of associated organizations. Among the many witnesses appearing on one side or the other were Herbert Aptheker, Louis F. Budenz, Paul Crouch, W. E. B. DuBois, Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, John Gates, Benjamin Gitlow, Joseph Zack Kornfeder, Harvey Matusow, Frank S. Meyer, Philip E. Mosely, William L. Patterson, Herbert A. Philbrick, Herbert Romerstein, Howard Selsam and Milton Wolff. The testimony and oral argument of counsel also document the intellectual and legal ground on which communist and subversion controversies were conducted.
Also included are the mimeographed decisions of the Board and a certain number of internal supporting documents used by the Board. The latter are mainly carbon copy typescripts.
Proceedings regarding organizations (by far the largest part of the records) are listed first, and proceedings regarding individuals afterwards. Within each of these two record groups, hearing transcripts appear first, followed by supporting documents and finally by Board decisions. Materials within each of these subdivisions are arranged by docket number, each docket number designating a separate case. Printed annual reports of the Board and bound compilations of its decisions appear last.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Communism--United States.; Subversive activities--United States.
Collection Contents
- Transcripts of Proceedings, 1950-1972. (Box 1-71)
  Mimeographed transcripts of hearing testimony and oral argument of counsel, arranged by docket number
  - Docket 51-101: Communist Party of the United States of America (Folder 1)
    - 1950 December 14-1951 May 8 (Folder 1)
    - 1951 May 9-June 6 (Folder 2)
    - 1951 June 7-July 9 (Folder 3)
    - 1951 July 10-26 (Folder 4)
    - 1951 July 30-September 24 (Folder 5)
    - 1951 September 25-October 31 (Folder 6)
    - 1951 November 1-December 5 (Folder 7)
    - 1951 December 6-1952 January 14 (Folder 8)
    - 1952 January 15-February 13 (Folder 9)
    - 1952 February 25-April 1 (Folder 10)
    - 1952 April 2-June 9 (Folder 11)
    - 1952 June 10-26 (Folder 12)
    - 1952 June 27-1956 December 11 (Folder 13)
    - 1958 May 14-1959 January 19 (Folder 14)
  - Docket 102-53: Labor Youth League (Folder 14)
    - 1953 May 14-December 9 (Folder 14)
    - 1953 December 10-1954 January 26 (Folder 15)
    - 1954 February 16-March 3 (Folder 16)
    - 1954 March 4-April 5 (Folder 17)
    - 1954 April 6-1962 March 1 (Folder 18)
  - Docket 103-53: International Workers Order, 1953 June 25-1954 January 4 (Folder 19)
  - Docket 104-53: National Council of American-Soviet Friendship (Folder 19)
    - 1953 May 13-1954 May 17 (Folder 19)
    - 1954 May 18-June 3 (Folder 20)
    - 1954 June 4-July 9 (Folder 21)
    - 1954 July 13-26 (Folder 22)
    - 1954 July 27-1955 September 8 (Folder 23)
  - Docket 105-53: Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee, 1953 May 13-1955 May 31 (Folder 24)
  - Docket 106-53: Civil Rights Congress (Folder 24)
    - 1954 November 15-December 7 (Folder 24)
    - 1954 December 8-1955 January 3 (Folder 25)
    - 1955 January 4-19 (Folder 26)
    - 1955 February 8-17 (Folder 27)
    - 1955 February 21-May 3 (Folder 28)
    - 1955 May 9-23 (Folder 29)
    - 1955 May 24-1962 February 14 (Folder 30)
  - Docket 107-53: Jefferson School of Social Science (Folder 30)
    - 1953 May 13-December 9 (Folder 30)
    - 1953 December 10-1954 January 14 (Folder 31)
    - 1954 January 15-May 14 (Folder 32)
    - 1954 May 17-1962 May 11 (Folder 33)
  - Docket 108-53: Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (Folder 34)
    - 1953 May 13-1954 May 18 (Folder 34)
    - 1954 May 19-June 10 (Folder 35)
    - 1954 June 15-September 13 (Folder 36)
    - 1954 September 14-27 (Folder 37)
    - 1954 September 30-1955 September 9 (Folder 38)
  - Docket 109-53: American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born (Folder 38)
    - 1953 May 14-1955 June 22 (Folder 38)
    - 1955 June 23-July 7 (Folder 39)
    - 1955 July 8-October 7 (Folder 40)
    - 1955 October 11-November 29 (Folder 41)
    - 1955 December 13-1956 January 11 (Folder 42)
    - 1956 January 12-31 (Folder 43)
    - 1956 February 1-1959 September 21 (Folder 44)
    - 1959 November 12-1965 July 13 (Folder 45)
  - Docket 110-53: Council of African Affairs, 1953 May 14 (Folder 45)
  - Docket 111-53: United May Day Committee (Folder 45)
    - 1953 July 16-1955 July 21 (Folder 45)
    - 1955 July 22-1956 April 20 (Folder 46)
  - Docket 112-53: American Slav Congress, 1953 July 17-1955 January 13 (Folder 46)
  - Docket 113-53: Committee for a Democratic Far Eastern Policy, 1953 May 14-1955 February 24 (Folder 46)
  - Docket 114-55: Washington Pension Union (Folder 47)
    - 1955 March 30-October 11 (Folder 47)
    - 1955 October 12-November 8 (Folder 48)
    - 1955 November 9-1956 February 28 (Folder 49)
    - 1956 February 29-May 21 (Folder 50)
    - 1957 January 16-1962 March 12 (Folder 51)
  - Docket 115-55: California Labor School (Folder 51)
    - 1955 December 5-1956 January 17 (Folder 51)
    - 1956 January 18-27 (Folder 52)
    - 1956 January 30-1962 April 16 (Folder 53)
  - Docket 116-56 (subsequently reopened as Docket 125-62): International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers (Folder 53)
    - 1955 October 27-1957 February 27 (Folder 53)
    - 1957 February 28-April 2 (Folder 54)
    - 1957 April 3-May 1 (Folder 55)
    - 1957 May 2-June 18 (Folder 56)
    - 1957 June 25-1960 April 18 (Folder 57)
    - 1960 April 19-October 5 (Folder 58)
    - 1960 October 6-November 15 (Folder 59)
  - Docket 116-56 (subsequently reopened as Docket 125-62): International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers (contd.) (Folder 60)
    - 1960 November 16-December 6 (Folder 60)
    - 1961 January 4-February 15 (Folder 61)
    - 1961 February 16-1963 January 23 (Folder 62)
    - 1963 January 24-February 15 (Folder 63)
    - 1963 February 18-July 2 (Folder 64)
  - Docket 117-56: American Peace Crusade (Folder 64)
    - 1955 November 1-1956 April 5 (Folder 64)
    - 1956 April 10-1962 January 25 (Folder 65)
  - Docket 118-56: National Negro Labor Council, 1955 December 9 (Folder 65)
  - Docket 119-56: United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (Folder 65)
    - 1956 March 28-1957 May 27 (Folder 65)
    - 1957 May 28-September 9 (Folder 66)
  - Docket 120-57: Colorado Committee to Protect Civil Liberties, 1957 July 16-1962 March 2 (Folder 66)
  - Docket 121-57: Connecticut Volunteers for Civil Rights, 1957 June 18-19 (Folder 66)
  - Docket 123-57: California Emergency Defense Committee, 1957 March 1-May 6 (Folder 67)
  - Docket 124-57: Committee to End Sedition Laws (Folder 67)
    - 1957 June 18-25 (Folder 67)
    - 1957 June 26-July 2 (Folder 68)
  - Docket 126-63: Advance, an Organization of Progressive Youth (Folder 68)
    - 1963 September 30-October 7 (Folder 68)
    - 1963 October 8-30 (Folder 69)
    - 1963 October 31-1965 July 29 (Folder 70)
  - Docket 128-71: Center for Marxist Education, 1970 November 17-18 (Folder 71)
  - Docket 129-71: Young Workers Liberation League, 1970 December 17-1972 February 8 (Folder 71)
- Supporting Documents, 1954-1963. (Box 71-73)
  Typewritten indexes, lists, and summaries
  - Transcript transmission cover sheets (Folder 71)
  - Indexes of witnesses (Folder 72)
  - Docket 116-56: International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers (Folder 72)
    - Lists of exhibits (Folder 72)
    - Summaries of testimony (Folder 72)
    - Summaries of testimony (contd.) (Folder 73)
    - Analysis of Fred Gardner testimony (Folder 73)
- Findings, 1952-1973. (Box 74-76)
  Mimeographed decisions of the Board, arranged by docket number
  - Docket 51-101: Communist Party of the United States of America. Recommended decision, 1952; report of the Board, 1953; memorandum opinion and order of the Board, 1956; modified report of the Board, 1956; recommended decision on second remand proceeding, 1958; modified report of the Board on second remand, 1959 (Folder 74)
  - Docket 102-53: Labor Youth League. Recommended decision, 1954; report of the Board, 1955; report of the Board on remand, 1962 (Folder 74)
  - Docket 104-53: National Council of American-Soviet Friendship. Recommended decision, 1955; report and order of the Board, 1956 (Folder 74)
  - Docket 106-53: Civil Rights Congress. Recommended decision, 1955; report and order of the Board, 1957; report of the Board on remand, 1962 (Folder 75)
  - Docket 107-53: Jefferson School of Social Science. Recommended decision, 1954; report and order of the Board, 1955; report of the Board on remand, 1962 (Folder 75)
  - Docket 108-53: Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Report and order of the Board, 1955 (Folder 75)
  - Docket 109-53: American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born. Recommended decision, 1957; report and order of the Board, 1960; report of the Board on reconsideration, 1962 (Folder 75)
  - Docket 111-53: United May Day Committee. Recommended decision, 1956; report and order of the Board, 1956 (Folder 75)
  - Docket 112-53: American Slav Congress. Report and order of the Board, 1955 (Folder 75)
  - Docket 113-53: Committee for a Democratic Far Eastern Policy. Recommended decision, 1955; report and order of the Board, 1955 (Folder 75)
  - Docket 114-55: Washington Pension Union. Recommended decision, 1956; report and order of the Board, 1959; report of the Board on remand, 1962 (Folder 75)
  - Docket 115-55: California Labor School. Recommended decision, 1957; report and order of the Board, 1957; report of the Board on remand, 1962 (Folder 75)
  - Docket 116-56 (subsequently reopened as Docket 125-62): International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers. Memorandum ruling on questions certified to the Board by Board member-examiner, 1959; recommended decision, 1961; report and order of the Board, 1962; memorandum ruling and order on motions addressed to the petition, 1962; ruling on respondent's motion to strike testimony, 1963; report and order of the Board dismissing petition, 1963 (Folder 75)
  - Docket 117-56: American Peace Crusade. Recommended decision, 1956; modified report of the Board on reconsideration, 1957; report of the Board on remand, 1962 (Folder 76)
  - Docket 119-56: United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America. Report of the Board and order dismissing petition, 1959 (Folder 76)
  - Docket 120-57: Colorado Committee to Protect Civil Liberties. Recommended decision, 1957; report and order of the Board, 1959; report of the Board on remand, 1962 (Folder 76)
  - Docket 121-57: Connecticut Volunteers for Civil Rights. Recommended decision, 1957; report and order of the Board, 1959 (Folder 76)
  - Docket 123-57: California Emergency Defense Committee. Recommended decision, 1957; report and order of the Board, 1959 (Folder 76)
  - Docket 126-63: Advance and Burning Issues Youth Organization, Formerly Known as Advance. Recommended decision, 1964; notice of supplemental findings of fact and conclusions of law, 1964; memorandum to accompany order placing case in indefinite abeyance, 1965 (Folder 76)
  - Docket 128-71: Center for Marxist Education. Report and order of the Board, 1973 (Folder 76)
  - Docket 129-71: Young Workers Liberation League. Report and order of the Board, 1973 (Folder 76)
- Transcripts of Defunct Organization Proceedings, 1971-1972. (Box 76)
  Mimeographed transcripts of proceedings to verify defunct status of organizations.
  - Mimeographed transcripts of proceedings to verify defunct status of organizations. Dockets E72-001 through E72-201 and E73-202 through E73-233: 233 defunct organizations on Attorney General's subversive organizations list, 1971 November 22-1972 September 29 (Folder 76)
- Transcripts of Individual Case Proceedings, 1962-1969. (Box 77-85)
  - List of cases (Folder 77)
  - Docket I-1-62: William Albertson., 1962 July 2-September 24 (Folder 77)
  - Docket I-2-62: Miriam Friedlander., 1962 July 2-October 4 (Folder 77)
  - Docket I-3-62: Arnold Samuel Johnson., 1962 July 2-October 5 (Folder 77)
  - Docket I-4-62: William L. Patterson., 1962 July 2-October 10 (Folder 78)
  - Docket I-5-62: Betty Gannett Tormey., 1962 July 2-October 16 (Folder 78)
  - Docket I-6-62: Louis Weinstock., 1962 July 2-October 23 (Folder 78)
  - Docket I-7-62: Dorothy Healey., 1962 July 2-November 8 (Folder 78)
  - Docket I-8-62: Albert Jason Lima., 1962 July 2-November 19 (Folder 78)
  - Docket I-9-62: Burt Gale Nelson., 1962 July 2-November 26 (Folder 78)
  - Docket I-10-62: Roscoe Quincy Proctor., 1962 July 2-November 19 (Folder 78)
  - Docket I-11-63: Samuel Krass Davis., 1963 January 29 (Folder 78)
  - Docket I-12-63: Claude Mack Lightfoot., 1963 January 23-24 (Folder 80)
  - Dockets I-13-63 and I-14-63: Flora Hall and Samuel Kushner., 1963 February 18 (Folder 80)
  - Docket I-15-63: George Aloysius Meyers., 1963 July 1-August 7 (Folder 80)
  - Docket I-16-63: Thomas Nabried., 1963 June 17-August 7 (Folder 80)
  - Docket I-17-63: Mildred McAdory Edelman., 1963 June 3-July 3 (Folder 80)
  - Docket I-18-63: Irving Potash., 1963 June 4-July 3 (Folder 80)
  - Docket I-19-63: William Wolf Weinstone., 1963 June 5-July 3 (Folder 81)
  - Docket I-20-63: Mortimer Daniel Rubin., 1963 June 10-July 3 (Folder 81)
  - Docket I-21-63: John William Stanford, Jr., 1963 September 23-November 4 (Folder 81)
  - Docket I-22-63: Benjamin Dobbs., 1963 September 24-November 4 (Folder 81)
  - Docket I-23-63: William Cottle Taylor., 1963 September 25-November 4 (Folder 81)
  - Dockets I-24-63 and I-25-63: Frances Gabow and Aaron Libson., 1963 October 2-November 4 (Folder 81)
  - Docket I-26-63: Lionel Joseph Libson., 1963 December 18-1964 February 18 (Folder 81)
  - Docket I-27-63: James Joseph Tormey., 1963 December 18-1964 June 25 (Folder 82)
  - Docket I-28-64: Michael Saunders., 1964 July 27 (Folder 82)
  - Docket I-29-64: Daniel Lieber Queen., 1964 May 25-27 (Folder 82)
  - Dockets I-30-64 and I-31-64: Ralph William Taylor and Betty Mae Smith., 1964 March 17 (Folder 82)
  - Dockets I-32-64 and I-33-64: Marvin Joel Markman and Meyer Jacob Stein., 1964 March 24-April 10 (Folder 82)
  - Dockets I-34-64 and I-35-64: Norman Haaland and Benjamin Gerald Jacobson., 1964 April 7-10 (Folder 83)
  - Dockets I-36-64 and I-37-64: Milford Adolf Sutherland and Donald Andrew Hamerquist., 1964 April 14-18 (Folder 83)
  - Docket I-38-65: Hyman Lumer., 1964 December 14-21 (Folder 83)
  - Docket I-39-65: Elmer Charles Kistler., 1965 January 26-27 (Folder 83)
  - Docket I-40-65: Ralph Nelson., 1965 January 19-21 (Folder 83)
  - Dockets I-41-65, I-42-65, I-43-65 and I-44-65: Otis Archer Hood, Lewis Martin Johnson, Edward S. Teixeira and Anne Burlak Timpson., 1964 December 10-14 (Folder 83)
  - Dockets I-45-69 and I-46-69: Robert Archuleta and Wayne Dallas Holley., 1968 September 3-October 2 (Folder 83)
  - Dockets I-47-69, I-48-69 and I-49-69: Anna Pastor Laconich, Ruth Beer and Scarlett Ann Patrick., 1968 September 3-1969 March 18 (Folder 83)
  - Docket I-50-69: Simon Boorda., 1968 September 3-12 (Folder 85)
  - Docket I-51-69: Sargeant Caulfield., 1968 September 3 (Folder 85)
  - Dockets I-52-69 and I-53-69: Clifford Fried and David Utter Mares., 1969 June 17-18 (Folder 85)
  - Docket I-54-69: Kenneth William Applehans., 1969 July 1 (Folder 85)
- Individual Case Supporting Documents, 1962-1964. (Box 85)
  Indexes and certificates.
  - Indexes of witnesses and certificates of transcript authenticity, 1962-1964 (Folder 86)
- Individual Case Findings, 1962-1969. (Box 86-88)
  Mimeographed decisions of the Board, arranged by docket number.
  - Docket I-1-62: William Albertson. Report and order of the Board, 1962 (Folder 86)
  - Docket I-2-62: Miriam Friedlander. Report and order of the Board, 1962 (Folder 86)
  - Docket I-3-62: Arnold Samuel Johnson. Recommended decision, 1962; report and order of the Board (Folder 86)
  - Docket I-4-62: William L. Patterson. Recommended decision, 1962; report and order of the Board (Folder 86)
  - Docket I-5-62: Betty Gannett Tormey. Recommended decision, 1962; report and order of the Board (Folder 86)
  - Docket I-6-62: Louis Weinstock. Recommended decision, 1962; report and order of the Board, 1963 (Folder 86)
  - Docket I-7-62: Dorothy Healey. Report and order of the Board, 1962 (Folder 86)
  - Docket I-8-62: Albert Jason Lima. Recommended decision, 1962; report and order of the Board, 1963 (Folder 86)
  - Docket I-9-62: Burt Gale Nelson. Recommended decision, 1962; report and order of the Board, 1963 (Folder 86)
  - Docket I-10-62: Roscoe Quincy Proctor. Recommended decision, 1962; report and order of the Board, 1963 (Folder 86)
  - Docket I-11-63: Samuel Krass Davis. Report and order of the Board, 1963 (Folder 86)
  - Docket I-12-63: Claude Mack Lightfoot. Report and order of the Board, 1963 (Folder 86)
  - Docket I-13-63: Flora Hall. Recommended decision, 1963; report and order of the Board (Folder 86)
  - Docket I-14-63: Samuel Kushner. Recommended decision, 1963; report and order of the Board (Folder 86)
  - Docket I-15-63: George Aloysius Meyers. Recommended decision, 1963; report and order of the Board (Folder 86)
  - Docket I-16-63: Thomas Nabried. Recommended decision, 1963; report and order of the Board (Folder 86)